<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true discourse of the wonderfull victorie, obteined by Henrie the fourth, the French King, and King of Nauarre, in a battell against those of the League, neere the towne of Yurie, on the Plaine of Saint Andrew, the foureteenth day of March (according to the French account) in the yeare 1590. Added thereto first, certaine newes that happened since the said ouerthrow of the Duke of Maine. Also an extract of things registred in the Court of Parliament. And further, an acte of Parliament against such as harbour and aide rebells and theeues, helping them to passe and repasse the riuers. Compiled and sent hither by one of the principall officers of the Kings Maiestie.</title>
            <title>Vray discours de la victoire merveilleuse obtenue par le roy de france pres d'Yury le 14. de Mars 1590. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13974</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99892183</idno>
  <idno type="VID">190336</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240914412</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">STC 13145</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.132.h.25[9]</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99892183</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99892183e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13974)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 190336)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C20:1[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true discourse of the wonderfull victorie, obteined by Henrie the fourth, the French King, and King of Nauarre, in a battell against those of the League, neere the towne of Yurie, on the Plaine of Saint Andrew, the foureteenth day of March (according to the French account) in the yeare 1590. Added thereto first, certaine newes that happened since the said ouerthrow of the Duke of Maine. Also an extract of things registred in the Court of Parliament. And further, an acte of Parliament against such as harbour and aide rebells and theeues, helping them to passe and repasse the riuers. Compiled and sent hither by one of the principall officers of the Kings Maiestie.</title>
                  <title>Vray discours de la victoire merveilleuse obtenue par le roy de france pres d'Yury le 14. de Mars 1590. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Orwin for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, with additions, of "Le vray discours de la victoire merveilleuse obtenue par le roy de france pres d'Yury le 14. de Mars 1590" (STC 13144).</note>
                  <note>The act of parliament referred to in the title was promulgated 27 January 1590--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi² B-E⁴ F³.</note>
                  <note>Printers' device on t.p. (McK. 273) head-piece, initial.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">France --  History --  Henry IV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:190336:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:190336:1"/>
            <p>The true discourse of the wonderfull <hi>victorie, obteined by Henrie the fourth, the</hi> French King, and King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> in a battell against <hi>those of the League, neere the towne of</hi> Yurie, <hi>on the Plaine</hi> of Saint Andrew, the foureteenth day of March (according to the French account) In the yeare 1590.</p>
            <p>Added thereto first, certaine newes that happened since the said ouerthrow of the Duke of <hi>Maine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Also an extract of things registred in the Court of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And further, an acte of Parliament against such as harbour and aide Rebells and theeues, helping them to passe and repasse the riuers.</p>
            <p>Compiled and sent hither by one of the principall Officers of the Kings Maiestie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Psal. 68. verse 21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>God shall wound the head of his enemies: and the hairie scalpe of such a one as goeth on still in his wickednesse.</p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by Thomas Orwin for Thomas Man. 1590.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:190336:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:190336:2"/>
            <head>THE TRVE DISCOVRSE, OR setting downe of the wonderfull victorie obteined by <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth French King, and of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> in a battaile giuen against the rebels of the League, neare to the Towne of <hi>Yury,</hi> in the plaine of <hi>S. Andrew,</hi> on the fourteenth day of March (according to the French ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt). In the yeare of our Lord. 1590.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Arre and fire haue such re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblance together, that when as the one of thē mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth with a matter that is of it selfe fit &amp; readie to burne, it slaketh not to set it on a flame; and contrariwise if it come to the stubbe of a tree that is moist and earthie, it maketh it moulder to ashes before that any sparkle can be seene: likewise when the other (namely warre) once enflameth a valorous mynde, it maketh a mā take great paines, and aduenture vpon many perils, neuer staying vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he make his valour knowne: but warre maketh a coward more cowardly mynded; and the nearer that he is to danger, the lesse force and valour is in him to helpe himselfe. Proofes wherof daily haue
<pb facs="tcp:190336:3"/>been seene in the dealings betwixt the king &amp; his enemies, so as there hath not escaped a day since his comming to the Crowne, but triall hereof hath been made. But among al exāples, that of this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie victory which it pleased GOD to giue him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them in the battaile which was neare <hi>Yurie</hi> on the fourteenth day of this moneth, exceedeth the residue, and is so famous and memorable, that it is well worthie to be set forth in writing, &amp; that this writing be confirmed with good testimonies. For otherwise the truer that the thing shall be, the lesse credit will be giuen thereto.</p>
            <p>Whilest that the king by sieges and assaults re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered in lesse then a moneth eight or ten of the best towns of base <hi>Normandie,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Mayne</hi> threatened and boasted daily, that hee needed not come thether with his Armie, and make him rayse his siege, for he would meete himselfe at the town of <hi>Honfleur,</hi> which is a hauen towne by the sea: but he neuer went about any such matter. His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie on the contrarie part neuer threatened, but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing recouered the said towne of <hi>Honfleur,</hi> came to make him raise his siege. He had then, about fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene dayes before, the towne and fort of <hi>Meulan,</hi> being distant from the said <hi>Honfleur</hi> about three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score myles: and there hauing offered him battaile, which he had great reason to accept (for his forces were as great as any that the king could then haue; yet the said Duke of <hi>Mayne,</hi> not respecting this his aduantage, which was sufficient to haue encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him, would not at that tyme ioyne battaile; but
<pb facs="tcp:190336:3"/>vnderstanding that fifteen hundred Launciers, and foure or fiue hūdred Harquebuziers on horseback, that were sent him out of the Low Coūtries, were now entred into <hi>France,</hi> he went to muster them.</p>
            <p>And while the kings Maiestie resolued himself to take the first opportunity offered him to besiege the towne of <hi>Dreux,</hi> whereas were assembled my maisters the <hi>Prior</hi> and Marshal of <hi>Aumont,</hi> and the Lord of <hi>Giury,</hi> who brought him good companies of souldiours. A little before hee came to the said siege, euen as hee was giuing the onset, word was brought him, that the Duke de <hi>Mayne</hi> hauing ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him his said forces of strangers, whose leader and Generall was the Conte <hi>Egmond,</hi> had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out speaches that he would go and encounter forthwith with the kings Army, promising and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suring his partakers, that hee would bid the king battaile wheresoeuer he could meete him. And in deede his Maiestie vnderstood that he was turning towarde the Riuer of <hi>Seyne,</hi> so to passe ouer the Bridge of the town of <hi>Mante,</hi> which held on their side, being from <hi>Dreux</hi> but seuenteen or eighteen myles.</p>
            <p>Hereupon his Maiestie, albeit hee considered, that as for the Duke of <hi>Mayne,</hi> whose forces were but borrowed, he had no other way but to go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward now speedily, &amp; to aduenture now or neuer; and as for him, staying for a time might bring him aduantage; that he had forces of strangers in <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne</hi> comming to meete him, that would bee as good as those of <hi>Flanders</hi> that the enemy had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten:
<pb facs="tcp:190336:4"/>that the hazard of warre was dangerous, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in those quarters where he was so far from succour, and cōsidering that those which offer the iniurie are commonlie more desperate in assaultes then they that withstand the iniurie: notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all this hee had other reasons mouing him which were more forcible and substantiall, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the most certaine (as I thinke) was the sure confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that he reposed in the goodnes of God, and equitie of his cause, hoping also well, by meanes of the knowledge that hee had of those with whom he had to deale, (they of <hi>Arques</hi> and other places, who had alwayes kept their possessions, being for his sake now driuen to flie and suffer wrong, who he resolued not to make loose their labour.) And being now certainlie informed that the said Duke of <hi>Mayne</hi> and his Armie, was whollie passed and come to the towne of <hi>Dammartin,</hi> which was but foure myles before; his Maiestie departed from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Dreux</hi> on Monday being the twelfth day, and began to make his Armie march thence in battaile ray, in such sort as those of the towne were well pleased to see them thus marching away as they stood on the walles.</p>
            <p>The same day came his Maiestie and lodged in the towne of <hi>Nonencourt,</hi> which towne hee had won a little before. This he did because he would cut off the passage of a little Riuer that runneth thereby. As soone as he was come thether, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed warning to be giuen that on the next morning euery bodie should be in a readynes; that euening
<pb facs="tcp:190336:4"/>and night his Maiestie deuised and set in order the maner and plot of his battaile, which in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he declared to Mōsieur <hi>Montpensier</hi> my Lords the Marshals of <hi>Biron</hi> and of <hi>Aumont,</hi> Baron <hi>Biron</hi> Lord Marshall of the field, and other the principall Captaines of the said Armie, who all with one voice allowed thereof so well, and that with such iudgement and militarie wisedome, as they would change nothing thereof. He then gaue in charge to the said Lord <hi>Biron</hi> for to set euery man in his place and order. He chose the said morning the Lord of <hi>Wich,</hi> who is one of the auncient maisters of the field for the footemen in <hi>France,</hi> Sergeant of the battaile. Which choise was liked and commē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of all men, for because he was a man well wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of that charge.</p>
            <p>This being done, his Maiestie was willing to begin this great worke with an holy prayer, which he made opēly vnto God, calling him there to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse that he knew the purpose of his heart, &amp; well vnderstood whether it were for desire of bloud, longing for reuenge, or any desire of glorie or am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition which made him resolute to this battaile; that he was his iudge and witnes vnreproueable, that nothing moued him hereto but the tēder loue that he did beare to his poore people, whose pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable &amp; quiet good estate he esteemeth more thā the safetie of his owne life: he besought God, so to direct his will as hee should best see to be good for the benefit of Christendome: and as for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, he prayed God so to saue and helpe him as he
<pb facs="tcp:190336:5"/>should know to be good &amp; profitable to the weale and quiet of that estate, and not otherwise. This Prayer, eloquent in wordes, but more passing pure and deuoute in meaning; did so rauish all those that were nigh, that euery man after his example did the like.</p>
            <p>Then was seen in <hi>Nonencourt</hi> the Churches full of Princes, Lords, Gentlemen and souldiours of all nations, hearing Masse, communicating, and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Catholikes. Those of the Religion made their humble prayers and supplications vnto God.</p>
            <p>This being done, a man would haue iudged by their countenances, that euery one had receiued an assured reuelation from his seuerall good angell, of the happie successe that euery each of them should obteine. His Maiestie then caused a summons of yelding to be made vnto the towne of <hi>S. Andrew,</hi> being from <hi>Nonencourt</hi> aforesaid eight myles, in the way going to <hi>Yurie,</hi> where he supposed that the enemy and his Armie was lodged. About the said towne vpon a great plaine standing in the sight of certaine other villages, and of a little wood cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>La Haye des pres,</hi> all the sayd companies came: his Maiestie with the Marshals <hi>Biron</hi> and <hi>Aumont</hi> and the foresaid Lord Baron <hi>Biron</hi> Marshall of the field, began to set the battaile in order, following the plot that they had agreed vpon before; the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner whereof was thus.</p>
            <p>His Maiestie who had tryed in other battailes and skirmishes before, that it is more aduantage for to make the horsemen fight in squadrons then in
<pb facs="tcp:190336:5"/>ryngs, especially his that haue no Launces, deuided all his said horsemen into seuen Regiments, ranged in so many squadrons, and all his footemen to the flankes of the said squadrons, euery one of which had a companie of forlorne footemen. The front of the said Armie was as it were in a rightlyne, yet making a little difference at the two ends. The first squadron on the left side, was that of Monsieur the Marshall of <hi>Aumōt,</hi> which might be of some three hundred good horsemen, hauing on his two sides twelue Regiments of French footemen. The secōd was that of Monsieur <hi>Montpensier,</hi> which also was of three hundred horses, and had on his left side foure or fiue hundred Lansquenets; on the right side a Regiment of Switzers, euery one of the said strange forces being lyned with French footemen. A little before the said squadrons was that of the light horsemen in two companies, the one where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was Monsieur the great <hi>Prior</hi> Colonell thereof, and in the other the Lord of <hi>Giurie</hi> Marshall of the field of the said light horsemen, which was able to make foure hundred good horses: a little more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the left hand was the Artillerie, which was 4. Canōs &amp; 2. Culuerins. The fourth squadrō was that of the said Lord Baron of <hi>Biron,</hi> which might be of 250. horses: and in the same ranke or order a little on the left hand, toward Monsieur <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensier</hi> was a companie of light horsemen. The fift squadron, was the kings, which made fiue rankes, in euerie one of which was six score good horse: he had on the left side two Regiments of Switzers
<pb facs="tcp:190336:6"/>of the Cantons of <hi>Glaris</hi> and of <hi>Grisons,</hi> and on his right side a great battaillon of two other Regimēts of Switzers, the one of the Canton of <hi>Soleurre,</hi> and the other of the Colonell <hi>Balthasar:</hi> which was in the whole of eighteen ensignes: euery of the said battaillons hauing his wings, to wit, on the right hand the Regiment of the gardes of <hi>Brigueux,</hi> on the left wing those of <hi>Vignols</hi> and of <hi>S. Iohn.</hi> Then was the companie of the Marshall of <hi>Biron,</hi> which was of two hundred and fiftie good horse, hauing with him two Regiments of French footemen. Then were the Reisters which had ioyned with them French footemen, like as other cōpanies had.</p>
            <p>Things being thus set in order, the king and my said Lordes the Marshall and Baron <hi>Biron</hi> so plyed the matter, that in lesse than an houre all was so or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and disposed, as none could haue more lyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie pourtrayed the same, &amp; while his Maiestie had thus set in order his battaile, came the Prince of <hi>Contie,</hi> with his horsemen &amp; some footmen. There came also the Lord of <hi>Guiche,</hi> great Maister of the ordinance, and the Lord of <hi>Plessis Mornay,</hi> to whō, vpon deliberation had, was graunted a place in his Maiesties squadron.</p>
            <p>In the meane while, were sent light horsemen for spyes on the left side of the battaile, supposing that the enemy lay at <hi>Yurie,</hi> which is a great towne hauing a Bridge ouer the Riuer <hi>Dure,</hi> thinking there to go and set vpon them: but they had not passed halfe a myle, before they perceiued and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood, that the enemy was more ware of the
<pb facs="tcp:190336:6"/>matter than they thought, and was passed the riuer <hi>Dure,</hi> and that he began to shewe himselfe in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell ray. But this his speed in passing the riuer was not, for that he thought to haue found the Kinges army so neare. And contrariwise, the King hearing of their going to <hi>Verneuill,</hi> thought to haue mett them there, and so went thither, whither indeede the enemy had sent his harbengers for to take vp lodgings, euen neare the place where his Maiesties army lay.</p>
            <p>As soone as these newes of the enemies shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himselfe in the fielde came, there was seene great ioy throughout the whole army, and his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie then caused his companies to march on a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle from the place where he was, and had not gone farre, but that he espied, not farre off and between both the armies there was a village holden by the enemy, which the King made straight way yeelde vnto him. His Maiestie hauing thus giuen them occasion to offer him battell, yet the enemies did not stirre.</p>
            <p>The King nowe seeing, that it grew to be late and neare the sunne setting, and hauing not yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scryed the maner of their lodging their campe, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered notwithstanding by some likelihoods, that they lay now at some aduantage, wherevpon hee was aduised not to march then any further with his army, but stayed there, sending skoutes for to descry the enemy, and to make continuall skirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes with them: But the valour and resolution of those on the Kings side, &amp; those of the enemy, was
<pb facs="tcp:190336:7"/>vnlike, for twelue of the Kings men were too hard for foure and twentie of the enemy. There were prisoners taken, who reported, that the number of their souldiours was greater than they were aware of, and that they were giuen to vnderstande, howe that those on the Kings side were come thither ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for a fashion than minding to bid battell.</p>
            <p>In the meane while came companies from the garrisons of <hi>Deepe,</hi> and from <hi>Arch,</hi> &amp; other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of lords and gentlemen from <hi>Normandie,</hi> to the value of two hundred good horse and more, which were placed, some in the regiment of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>Montpensier,</hi> and some of them vnder the king, and some with Seigneur <hi>Biron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The two armies lay all a whole day thus in sight the one of the other, not medling the one with the other, except it were some odde skirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes, and the taking of the village aforesaide. In the end night drewe on, and they were constrained to take vp their lodgings. The King himselfe was lodged at <hi>Foncrainuille,</hi> which is a little village on the left hand of the plaine aforesaid, whereas the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the King was first set in battell ray. The resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of the armie was lodged in other Villages, which those of the league had thought to haue sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised the same day. The King as he was the first in the morning that offered battel, so he he was the last that was at euening in the field, and woulde not depart thence before that he saw the manner of the enemies lodging, &amp; had set al his watches in order.</p>
            <p>His Maiestie being in the ende come to his lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,
<pb facs="tcp:190336:7"/>which was two houres within night, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a little refreshed himselfe, sent worde vnto his men, that euery one of them should be in a readines against the morning: and hee was stirring in the morning very early himselfe: for when he had ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en but two houres vpon a pallet, he presently sent to enquire news of the enemy. And first word was brought him, that the enemy seemed to be passed the riuer, because that in the place where the army lay, were fires, and no body could be discerned. He sent the second time, and then worde was brought him, that vndoubtedly the enemy was not passed the riuer, but they were lodged in the villages that lie about the riuer <hi>Eure</hi> behind the said place where their army was supposed to haue bin. And moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it was reported, that they were not like now to passe the riuer; for if they woulde haue doone it, they would haue passed in the night time. These newes cheared his Maiestie, who did not omit this occasion offered. He began this day as he did the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther afore, with a most deuout prayer vnto God, and that before his men, for he liueth among men, as thinking that hee is continually seene and heard of God.</p>
            <p>Day light being come, the Princes and my said Lords the Marshals came to his Maiestie &amp; set their men in battell ray the best that they could deuise. Then his Maiestie went to breakfast: the said Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Marshals and other Lords hauing heard Masse and done their deuotions, went to refresh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues. And albeit this night had beene trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some
<pb facs="tcp:190336:8"/>to the most, for that they were driuen to lye in the fielde. Yet they hearing certaine newes, that the same day they shoulde ioyne battell, did so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, as the ioyfull thinking on that day did driue away all the remembrance of the pains and trouble that they had taken the same night and the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. About nine of the clocke, the King came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the field, and a little before were all the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies in order, vpon warning giuen by two Canon shot that were discharged at eight of the clocke: and euery man at his comming knewe his place, so as by ten of the clocke in the forenone all the army was in order.</p>
            <p>The hoste of the enemies was at the same tyme raysed and remooued a little further off than it was the day before. The order and manner of setting the battell was like that of his Maiestie sauing the winges which were a little more outward than those of the King: But as the cornet of his Maiesty was in the middest of his squadrons, so was that of the Duke of <hi>Maine,</hi> but his cornet was in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest of two squadrons of lances of those that were come out of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> which might be of some twelue or thirteene hundred horse. The said cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of the foresaid duke of <hi>Maine</hi> might be of two hundred and fiftie horse, and as many of the Duke of <hi>Nemours,</hi> which came to ioine with him: which made a third squadron in the middle of the other two squadrons of lances, and the whole might be eighteene hundred horses which marched still to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. And herevpon the Duke of <hi>Nemours</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:190336:8"/>knight of <hi>Aumale</hi> thought themselues verie sure in this great squadron, the one of them being colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell of the light horsemen, the other of the foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. On the sides of the said squadron were their two regimentes of Switzers being also lined wyth French footemen. Then were there two other squadrons of Lances: on the right hand were light horsemen, some <hi>French,</hi> some <hi>Albanoys,</hi> and some <hi>Italians:</hi> on the left side were <hi>Wallons,</hi> and <hi>Spaniards:</hi> in the middle betweene both were footmen aswell French as lansquenets. The two wings were two great companies of Reisters, which might be on the right wing seauen hundred horse, and on the left fiue hundred. They had but two Culuerines, and two bastard Culuerines, which lay on their left wing.</p>
            <p>The King vnderstanding, that the enemy was wilfully bent and woulde not come forward, was resolute, and went toward them: and hauing mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched about a hundred and fiftie paces, got by that meane aduantage both of sunne and winde (which else would haue not a little troubled his men, and is a great aduantage in warre) Drawing neare, he and his captaines perceiued that his enemies were moe in number than they thought: for they were iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be foure thousand horse, and ten or twelue thousand footemen: yet this did but increase their courage the more.</p>
            <p>The army of those of the league was the more charged with golde and siluer, that of the King ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with yron and steele: and there could not be a
<pb facs="tcp:190336:9"/>more terrible sight than to see a two thousand gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen in compleate armour from top to the toe, burning in affection vpon so good an occasion as this, to doe their King and countrie good seruice, &amp; by this meane to seeke the conseruation of their goods and houses, which they sawe then like to be made a pray for strangers.</p>
            <p>This their resolution, as it prooued, was better than twice so much force: for it is not the number that maketh the matter. His Maiestie being in the forefront of his squadron (the fore ranke of which was of Princes, Earles, and Knightes of the Holie Ghost, and other principall Lordes and Gentlemen of the chiefe houses in <hi>France</hi>) began againe to pray vnto God, and exhorted euery one to doe the like, as indeede they did with so feruent a zeale as pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into heauen. The King then went from his squadron, and walked vp and downe his army, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging euery one with great modestie, shewing himselfe resolute and vndoubted of the victorie. Hee was no sooner come to his place againe, but Monsieur <hi>Marriuault</hi> was come thither, who did bring newes, that certaine companies of <hi>Picardie,</hi> which were vnder the leading of Monsieur de <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miers,</hi> Monsieur de <hi>Moüy,</hi> and other Lords and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen (which might bee of some two hundreth horse) were within two miles of them. Herevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as if he had been directed by the Spirit of God, who should set him downe his houre when to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, he would not driue off a iot, but sent comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to the Lord of <hi>Guich,</hi> to cause him shoote,
<pb facs="tcp:190336:9"/>which he did straight wayes, and that with such aduantage, as the enemies receiued thereby, great hurt; for there were discharged on the Kings side, nine canon shot before that the other could begin.</p>
            <p>After three or foure volees of shot passed on the one side and the other, the squadron of their ancient light horsemen, as well <hi>French,</hi> and <hi>Italians,</hi> as <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banoys,</hi> which might be of some fiue or six hundred horse, came to giue charge to Monsieur the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shall of <hi>Aumont,</hi> carrying with them the Lansque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets which were on their sides. But the said Lord Marshall willing to begin the combat, set vpon the enemy so hardly, as that he made them scatter, so as within a while a man coulde see nothing but their backes and horse tailes, chasing them to a little wood on the backe side, whereas the saide Lorde Marshall stayed, attending the kings comming, like as he had in charge. During this chase came the company of the Reisters on the right hand, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to haue come toward the Artillerie, but they found there light horsemen ready, which made them soone retire. Then came an other squadron of launces of <hi>Wallons</hi> and <hi>Flemings,</hi> seeing the saide light horse of the Kings a little off, by means of the combat betweene them and the company of Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, meaning to haue giuen them another charge: but the foresaid Lord Baron <hi>Biron</hi> shewed himself in fielde, and though hee could not meete with the forefront of the enemies battel, yet he so set on the reregarde, as that he shrewdly troubled them; and was there hurt himselfe both in the arme and face.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:190336:10"/>
            <p> My foresaid Lord <hi>Montpensier</hi> seeing so great an armie beeing of seauen hundred Spanish Laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and about foure hundred Carbines, Harquebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziers on horsebacke, hauing curets and murrions, vnder three great standarts that were vnder the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of Conte <hi>Egmond,</hi> set forward marching toward them, and gaue them such a charge, as that albeit he at the first was vnhorsed, yet he quicklie gat vp againe, and behaued himselfe so as that he brake their ray, and abode master of the field. At the same time the great squadron of the Duke of <hi>Mayne</hi> (which notwithstanding was not so great, as that it could with any aduantage encounter with the kings squadron) came marching to the battaile, hauing on the left wing foure hundred Harquebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziers on horseback, which they call Carbines, who gaue a volee of shot a fiue &amp; twentie paces of from his Maiesties squadron. This volee of shot being ended, the head of the said great squadron gaue bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile to the Kings squadron; in which the King behaued himselfe so valiantly, that whereas before in other matters he seemed to haue plaied the part of a great King and Captaine, in commanding and ordering of things, he in this fight seemed to play the part of a lustie braue soldier. This was a great and furious assault, and yet the great terrible forrest of their Launces could not breake his Maiesties ray; and on the contrariwise, that of the enemie was by him scattered and followed vpon with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie: but for a quarter of an houre there was hard fighting on both sides.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:190336:10"/>
            <p> In a short space this great companie of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies began so to weaken and to scatter, that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before they so lustilie shewed their faces in the battaile, they now began to turne the backe, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as they were, began to shewe their heeles.</p>
            <p>This beginning of victorie could not yet well like the Kings armie, because that they had lost the sight of the King; but within a while they espied him comming all berayed with the bloud of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and (God bee thanked) not hauing lost one drop of his owne bloud, and yet he was a marked man: for he had in his headpeece a great white bunch of feathers, and another sticking in his horse forehead: which gaue a terrour to the enemie, and made his friends greatlie to reioyce, seeing him thus to escape from the skirmish. But he was so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set, that as he was retiring to his companie, hauing with him not past twelue or fifteene men, he was set vpon by two battaillons of Switzers enemies, three companies of Wallons, and certeine other who did weare red crosses; whom his Maiestie did so couragiouslie set vpon, that he tooke away their Cornets, and killed there those that carried and garded them. When the King was thus come againe to his place, there was throughout the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie (as it were in token of thankes giuing vnto God for his safe returne) a generall crie; <hi>God saue the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being come, there came and ioyned with him the foresaid Lord Marshall of <hi>Aumont,</hi> with a great companie that he had gotten together, and among
<pb facs="tcp:190336:11"/>other came the Lord great Prior aforesaid with his men. At the same time also came Baron <hi>Biron,</hi> whom the King going to meete, found with his companie whole &amp; well, whereat the enemie was not a little discouraged, knowing well that this old Generall, who had been at the beginning of manie a battell in his life time, could good skill to end and breake this that was alreadie so sore shaken.</p>
            <p>The King was well apaied to see the field thus couered with the dead bodies of the enemies, and that none were left then in order but the Switzers, who had also lost their horsemen both on their right and left wings, and yet they still set a good countenance on the matter. He was once minded to haue sent French footmen to haue broken their ray on the right wing, which yet had not fought; but remembring the old friendship and league that had been betwixt those of this nation alwaies and the Crowne of <hi>France,</hi> was contented, and hauing sent Marshall <hi>Biron</hi> backe againe his men, offered them grace, and in stead of death which he might haue offered, he sent them life, which they receiued in great mercie. Then hauing laied downe their armes, they passed by his Maiestie: and the French that yeelded, found the like mercie.</p>
            <p>At the same instant when as he had ioyned with the said Lord Marshall of <hi>Biron,</hi> there met him the companies aforesaid out of <hi>Picardie.</hi> Then like as first he had plaied the part of a good Captaine and soldier, so he would now shewe himselfe a right Generall of an Armie, in pursuing a maine the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie.
<pb facs="tcp:190336:11"/>Therefore he setting forward the said Lord great Prior with a companie on the left side, and the foresaid Lord Baron <hi>Biron</hi> with another com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie on the right side, and hauing with him the residue of horsemen that were gathered together, and the foresaid companies that were come out of <hi>Picardie,</hi> he followed on the victorie, hauing in his companie my Lords the Princes of <hi>Contie</hi> and of <hi>Montpensier,</hi> the Conte <hi>S. Paule,</hi> and my foresaid Lords the Marshals of <hi>Aumont</hi> and of <hi>Trimouille,</hi> with infinite other Lords, Captaines and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the said Armie, leauing Marshall <hi>Biron</hi> with a great companie marching after.</p>
            <p>If the battell was not greatlie honorable to those of the League, their retiring was lesse honorable, for it was without order, not hauing in it any thing worthie the marking, sauing that feare seemed to make them at their wits end, and whereas they should haue marched toward the Kings power, they were seene running away from it. The said retyring was in two parts: the Duke of <hi>Nemours, Bassompiere,</hi> the Vicount of <hi>Tauanne, Rosne</hi> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine other tooke to <hi>Chartyes,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Mayne</hi> and a great sort of other tooke the way to <hi>Yurie,</hi> thinking to passe that riuer. And they had thought to haue carried also away their Ordinance, but that was not so speedilie to bee remooued, wherefore they were driuen to leaue it behind, as also they did all their baggage.</p>
            <p>The kings staying to pardō the Switzers, gaue the enemy great aduantage in their flying: so that whē
<pb facs="tcp:190336:12"/>his Maiestie came at <hi>Yurie,</hi> he found that the Duke of <hi>Mayne</hi> was passed a little before, and had broken the bridge after him, which caused the death and destruction of a great manie of his men, especiallie of the Reisters, a great sort of which were drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, some fearing to haue been taken by those that followed them in the chase, were glad to kill their horses for to helpe stop vp the passages in the streates. The bridge of <hi>Yurie</hi> being thus broken, and the passage there ouer the bridge being dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, his Maiestie was aduised to go and passe ouer the Riuer by a place called <hi>Annet,</hi> which is a great deale the better way, and was a three miles about: yet as hee went he found the wayes full of such as fled, who could not, by reason of their haste, be so well aduised of their way, as those on the Kinges side, which then did all things with discretion. Those that thought to haue escaped in the woods, fell into the handes of the country people, who v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed them more cruelly than the souldiers woulde haue done. His Maiestie pursued them vnto the Town of <hi>Mante</hi> so hotly, that none of them turned face backe once to see who folowed him: and had the Townesmen stood vnto their first resolution, which was, not to haue opened the gates, there had not beene left a man but he had beene either slaine or taken. In the ende, they being ouercome by the prayers and intreaties of the saide Duke of <hi>Mayne,</hi> yeelded to let him in, vpon condition that his reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue should passe by ten and ten that night ouer the bridge, if they would regard their safetie. His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie
<pb facs="tcp:190336:12"/>vnderstanding hereof, went and tooke vp his lodging at <hi>Rosny,</hi> a two mile from <hi>Mante</hi> aforesaid, as meanly prouided for that night as were the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>A man may rightely say, that this discomfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was such as had not lightly beene seene, for there was not a man on the kings side of any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count but woon honor; and on the other side they all went away with shame and losse. All the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were cut off sauing those that yeelded, and of them but a fewe saued. Of their horsemen were slaine and drowned aboue fifteene hundred, and foure hundred taken prisoners.</p>
            <p>Amongest those that were slaine were knowne for principall, the Conte <hi>Egmond</hi> knight of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Fleece, Colonell of the companies that the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> sent: the yoong Earle of <hi>Bruns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Chastaigneray,</hi> and many other, whose names are not knowen. Of prisoners were taken the Earle of <hi>Austfrist,</hi> of the house of <hi>Aust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frist,</hi> which was with the Reisters, and many lords strangers, as well <hi>Spaniards, Flemings,</hi> and <hi>Italians,</hi> as <hi>Frenchmen:</hi> the Lords of <hi>Boisdauphin Sigongne,</hi> who bare the white Cornet of the said Duke of <hi>Mayne: Mesdauid, Fontaine, Martell, Lochant, Lodon, Hugues<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>san, Falandre;</hi> the maisters of the field, <hi>Tenisay, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stelliere Descuneux</hi> and infinite other. There were aboue twenty Cornets of horsemen stayed, among which were their white Cornet; the great standard of the generall of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Flemings,</hi> and the Colonels Cornets of the Reisters, aboue three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score
<pb facs="tcp:190336:13"/>ensignes of footemen, as well French and Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings as lansquenets, besides foure and twenty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes of Switzers that yeelded themselues.</p>
            <p>Of his Maiesties army were slaine the Lords of <hi>Clermont,</hi> of <hi>Antragnes</hi> one of the Captaines of his Maiesties gardes, who deceased neare to the kings person, the Lord <hi>Tif Chombert,</hi> who hauing afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand commaunded and gouerned great charges of men himselfe, was now content to serue as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon souldiour in his Maiesties Cornet, the Lords of <hi>Longaulnay</hi> of <hi>Normandie,</hi> beeing of three score and ten yeares of age, of <hi>Crenay</hi> who was Cornet to Monsieur <hi>Montpensier,</hi> of <hi>Vienne</hi> who was lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant to the Lord of <hi>Benuron,</hi> which had that day a Cornet because his ensigne was not there, of <hi>Manneuille Vallois, Feiquiers,</hi> and a twenty other gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen at the most. There were hurt, the lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of <hi>Neste,</hi> who albeit hee was Captaine ouer a company of souldiours, yet he would needes fight in the fore ranke of the light horsemen, the Earle of <hi>Choisy,</hi> who had brought a good companie with him, the Lords of <hi>O,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Lude, Montlonet, Lauergne, Rosny,</hi> and it may be a twentie other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, most of which were not greatly hurt, nor had not any danger of death in them.</p>
            <p>The Nobilitie of <hi>Fraunce</hi> hath shewed it selfe hereby most apparantly nothing at all degenerate or swaruing from the steppes of their ancestours: but alwayes most affectionate towardes their king and lawful Prince, so that it may euidently appeare if any rebellion be, it must needes spring from the
<pb facs="tcp:190336:13"/>off-scome and race of rascall people, stirred vp by the factions and drifts of strangers, not so much by feare as by ambition. If euer any subiects did make their Prince beholding vnto them, it may now be said, that the king is much bounden and beholden vnto his Nobilitie, who came so voluntarily vnto his aide, without pay, without furniture, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most without any warning at all, and haue doone him so great a signall seruice. The King hath also made all his Nobilitie much beholding vnto him, to haue giuen them so great an occasion to emploie themselues, and to make triall of their fidelitie and valour, raising the honor and reputation of al their auncestors out of the dust. But euery man did am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply testify their gratefulnesse one to an other; first, the king vnto his subiects, in giuing them honors and preferrements according to their deserts; and then the subiects, in shewing the affection that they beare naturally vnto his Maiestie.</p>
            <p>In this combat two or three thinges haue fallen out so extraordinary and miraculous, that they may seeme to be verily wrought by the finger of God. The first is, that this Prince hath always had so firme a resolution to giue his enemies a battel by all meanes possible, with firme confidence, that the field and victorie should be his, and that no human reason or pollicy might dissuade him the contrary: albeit a man in other affaires very tractable, and one that referreth himselfe, and hearkeneth very much to the sage aduise and counsel of others. The other was that in the place where the battell was
<pb facs="tcp:190336:14"/>giuen, and euen at the instant when the fight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, it seemed that men as thicke as hoppes came from all parts to doe him seruice very well armed at all points. For ouer night, and vppon the day of battell, arriued more than sixe hundred horses: yet he was resolued without them there to fight it out: and the third is, that two thousand French Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (whereof neuer more than twelue hundreth fought) ouerthrewe and disordered a whole army of foure thousand horse, and twelue thousand foote, their horsemen fresh soldiers, brauely moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and well armed at all points.</p>
            <p>But the wrongfull cause they tooke in hand to defend, may be onely their excuse; for otherwise they can by no meanes diminish and empaire the glory of the conquerours, but by confessing that they were first ouerthrowne by their owne consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences before they came euer to the field to combat, whither they came like criminall persons condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to die, who by guiltinesse of conscience goe, as it were, halfe dead to the place of execution. For the very conceit and apprehension of punishment, is no lesse painefull than the paine it selfe, and most certaine it is, that he that seeks pains, suffreth paine: and he that deserueth it, seeketh it. <hi>France</hi> is in this beholding to them to thanke them that they are the cause, that strangers who neuer in thirtie yeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore drewe their swordes against the Nobilitie of <hi>France,</hi> may nowe certifie their Princes for trueth, that the very children strike as well as the fathers: and from henceforth they may content themselues
<pb facs="tcp:190336:14"/>to liue quiet at home, rather than to come to die here with dishonour, and to want christian butiall. The French that rest of this ouerthrowe, haue yet this comfort, that it is fallen out to them for the best to be ouercome: for nowe they may with euident reason and persuasion, voide of all lightnesse and rashnesse, resolue to withdraw themselues from the wicked counsels and practizes which they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hand before. The people acknowledging that the drifts of their Captaines are for their owne peculiar commoditie, and not for the matter they pretend and cloake. The Captaines hauing made experience, that honours and enuies of people may be held iust of one account, &amp; that as a man should not afflict himselfe for the one, so he should not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance himselfe too much by the other. In fine, that it is not with walls, but with men that warre must be made: besides that, they feele already what they haue lost, and that before they recouer it, they must feele some smart in open field, and it will be a long while before it come to that passe.</p>
            <p>But the greatest motiue that they ought to haue to make them resolue to take this fruit of their euil lucke is, the clemency and mercifulnes of the king, who hath in him no choller or gall inwardly hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, who breatheth nothing but bounty and all sweetnes and mercy, who spareth to spill the blood of his people more than his owne: that they may confesse that he hath in him all the good partes and qualities of a mighty and great King, &amp; of a great and puissant Captaine: and that God, who hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised
<pb facs="tcp:190336:15"/>&amp; preserued him in so many extraordinary dangers of war &amp; combats, hath vndoutedly reser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him for some great matter extraordinary: cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to be som <hi>Hercules</hi> to saue and deliuer vs frō al dangers: to be an <hi>Alexander</hi> to vnknit the knots of all leagued conspiracies, intricate complots, and confederat practises, wrapped, lincked, and fastned together. If they looke a farre off, they shall see &amp; confesse, that all their enterprises bended against him from time to time, haue serued to none other purpose, but to fortifie him, and make him still greater: So might this rebellion speede, the longer it lasteth, such successe might it haue, and no better. But it is greatly to be feared, that this great clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that his good nature doth offer now to his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient subiects, if it now be neglected and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of them, in the ende doe not turne into a rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous execution of iustice (as the wine, the sweeter it is, the more sooner it doth make the vineger.) Let them looke and take heede to this, if they be well aduised.</p>
            <p>The easiest and gainest way for reconcilement is by repentance, the greatest crimes make the best lawes: as they haue been cause of euill, so must they bee of good, and so may they also bee, and in such sort, that the fruite that shall come thereof, shall extinguish quite the remembrance of all our mischiefes passed and gone. God also himselfe doth giue vs so to vnderstand most manifestlie, helping the infirmitie of our iudgemēt, by miracles wought on earth, and signes shewed from heauen, as he did
<pb facs="tcp:190336:15"/>in the time when the faith was in his first age.</p>
            <p>It resteth now that God giue vs his grace, to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all things a right, and that we knowe also how to vse well the bountie and clemencie of our king, as he knoweth how to vse his victorie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it cannot bee truelie said that the issue and effect hath so much pleased him, as the cause doth dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>please him. Those of the townes of <hi>Mante</hi> and <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> where are two of the chiefest bridges ouer the riuer of <hi>Seyne,</hi> who yeelded themselues first vnto his clemencie, shalbe good witnesses whether their estate and condition bee pared or bettered. GOD graunt that the rest may follow this good example, and that the reunion vnto the obedience of his Maiestie may be as readie, as the meanes of reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and separation haue been swift and violent: that yet we may keep this age from being remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the posteritie, as it hath bin threatned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore by this of particides and murtherers of their countrie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>
               <hi>Newes happened since the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe</hi> of the Duke of <hi>Mayne.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAngrola</hi> the Legate and Monsieur <hi>de Ville-Roy,</hi> two collegues &amp; chief Agents of the League, seeing their affaires to haue ill successe, came incontinentlie after the victorie to busie the King a little, if by any meanes they might, making as much speede as they might in the meane time so to forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their partie, that without ayde from <hi>Spaine</hi> they
<pb facs="tcp:190336:16"/>might at their owne deuotion and greater aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, make truce and peace when they listed.</p>
            <p>It is surmised that <hi>Ville-Roy</hi> doth promise to sauegard his owne houses. <hi>Pontaise</hi> had thereof in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence. Monsieur <hi>de Plessis</hi> came to a parlie with him, handled him verie roughlie, and set him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath him at dinner. He offereth to iustifie himself, but Monsieur <hi>Beau-lieu</hi> (who is his sworne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie) opposeth himself to his reasons, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his faire promises by his practises with his old master, so that it is looked still when execution and iustice shall be done according to the Kings E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict.</p>
            <p>The Legate comming to parlie with Monsieur the Marshall of <hi>Biron,</hi> after manie salutations and blessings, wondered verie much that so great a troupe of Catholikes could followe an hereticall King. Whereunto Monsieur the Marshall made answere, that it nothing behoued them to looke so neere into that matter, that he held him for the true heire of the Crowne of <hi>France,</hi> that he had main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained their lawes vnuiolate, that he had for ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies none but strangers thrust forwards by ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who vnder shew and pretext of religion, went about to ouerthrowe all good lawes, and to giue an entrance to the Spanish King, and to set open the doore to all Atheisme. Whereupon he protested, that his master was free from medling in any of all those enterprises: but the whole storie hath been so wel auerred, and vowed by al the actions and parts past of his ambassage, and by his conuersation with
<pb facs="tcp:190336:16"/>
               <hi>Don Bernardin Mendoza,</hi> that he could denie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Thereupon he demanded the Marshall how they being by profession Catholikes, made so light accompt of his Holines purposes, &amp; carried armes against other their Catholike brethren. To that he answered, that herin he was of the <hi>Venetians</hi> minds: that they had a iust cause to defend, and in so doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it should bee verie good for the Pope to looke somewhat neerer to his owne estate, that if he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croched too much on them, they could excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate him quicklie; that there were diuers Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates in <hi>France</hi> as good Catholiks as the Pope, who would be very glad to be made Patriarches in their seuerall Prouinces, and should finde holy Scripture for the confirmation of their authoritie. Vpon this point they disputed a little, but <hi>Pangrola</hi> could not answere. In fine, he desired verie much to haue a good peace concluded, and that the conuersion of the King might bee sought, wishing that he might bee employed thereabout: and so they departed at that time without doing any good one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Parisians</hi> haue suffered their Gouernour to take in Switzers and Launce-knights into their ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the people is more hardned than euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. They haue found out all meanes possible to prolong and entertaine this warre. They haue now found out all the reliques for the purpose, but a great deale thereof is worth but little monie. The better sort and likeliest men are gone out of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, none abideth but the vulgar race of people, the
<pb facs="tcp:190336:17"/>verie scomme, and those that are almost driuen to despaire, the which, I feare, wil hazard the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to be fulfilled of them: Al things are very deare, and the Commons knowe not what to do for lack of traffique.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellieure</hi> came to finde the King, and was verie well receiued; in the end the King told him, that he thought in his conscience, that he was an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest man before the Queene Mother had got him to her side, and the company of <hi>Ville-Roy</hi> had spoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him. <hi>Brullard</hi> also came to the king, and was receiued with much fauour, and diuers others of <hi>Paris</hi> that pleaded their owne innocencie.</p>
            <p>Comming hither we passed by <hi>Cheureuse,</hi> where the King gaue a protection, and left behinde him for gouernor <hi>Sourdis</hi> the dutchesse of <hi>Guises</hi> man. We came hither on Satterday, much adoe had we to enter, and we were first resisted: but the morow after wee entered where the king stayed to heare some news from <hi>Melan</hi> and <hi>Laigny</hi> which are sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned. The Deputies of <hi>Laigny</hi> are come, the rest stand to their tackling, and are wilfull, and the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non shall depart to morrow: but they are obstinate &amp; stand vpon this point, for that they assure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, that the duke of <hi>Maine</hi> hath forces in <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagne,</hi> and hath promised them within fifteen days, either to bid the king battell, or else to put him to flight.</p>
            <p>It is most certaine, that he hath written to <hi>Paris</hi> himselfe: it is also most true, that he assembleth all his forces, and craueth aide from all partes; <hi>Ballag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:190336:17"/>dooth promise him fifteene hundred horses out of <hi>Picardie</hi> onely: he thinketh to recouer an other army of thirtie thousand men. Our <hi>Normans</hi> and others to the number of fifteene hundred horses retired themselues on Sonday last.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Langueuille</hi> and Monsieur de <hi>Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teuille</hi> are ariued with the Reisters, and are in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber more than eight thousand men, so that the K. is too strong for the enemy, and also sufficientlie fortified for all their enterprises.</p>
            <p>It is certaine, that all matters are driuen to this issue, that if the Duke of <hi>Maine</hi> doe not fight with vs speedily, all the authoritie of the league is rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; for it must needes be, that <hi>Paris</hi> yeelde for feare of famine, the passages rounde about beeing seised, or else it must be releeued, for it shall stande them somewhat vpon, being constrained therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by necessitie. But how his carriage shall holde out, I doubt, if dispaire doe not make him runne mad altogether, hauing lost a battell, for the losse whereof he hath beene astonied these many daies, and hath not doubted to confesse openly in <hi>Mante,</hi> that the king of <hi>Nauarre</hi> was alwayes luckie in all his attempts.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Auergne</hi> Monsieur de <hi>Rendan</hi> asseeging <hi>Issore</hi> hath had the repulse &amp; bin ouerthrowne in plaine field, fourescore Gentlemen of marke and qualitie being slaine in the place, the Artillery taken, and little of the infantery escaped. This ouerthrowe was giuen by the Seigneur of <hi>Chasseran</hi> and <hi>Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:190336:18"/>
            <p> Another ouerthrow was giuen nere vnto <hi>Metz,</hi> where Monsieur <hi>de Rieux</hi> tooke the Artillerie of the Duke of <hi>Lorraine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In base <hi>Normandie Viques</hi> and the Leaguers are ouerthrowne, &amp; Monsieur <hi>d'Allegre</hi> sent the King word, that two Castles about the forrest of <hi>Lyhons</hi> are yeelded to his obedience.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Brittanie</hi> diuers Regiments of Duke <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure</hi> were cut in peeces, but that is not sufficient to answer the losse of <hi>S. Malo,</hi> the death of the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and an hundred thousand crownes found in his coffers. All the townes begin to listen, and if no speedie aide come not from <hi>Spaine</hi> (for other suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour or contribution may not be hoped for) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt all the busines of the League shall bee vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlie ouerthrowne quicklie.</p>
            <p>This day is arriued a Post from <hi>Rome,</hi> with a <hi>Mandamus</hi> from the Pope to all Dukes, Counties and Barons, that they shall obey the King, and with expresse commandement to all the people to pray vnto God for him, and for the same purpose hath he sent vnto them a certaine forme of praier. I doo not knowe whether in this case the dealing and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring of Mounsieur of <hi>Luxembourg</hi> or the Holie ghost hath inspired him, but certaine it is, that the Pope is now become a Frenchman, highlie offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with his Legate, but a great deale more with the League, and demaundeth an accompt of fiftie thousand Crownes that he hath disbursed in the cause. Thereby you may see how the King is fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of GOD, and without doubt borne for the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine
<pb facs="tcp:190336:18"/>of the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi> His Maiestie is happie to haue his cause ioyned with Gods in this conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to haue ayded it in the beginning, when no bodie els put to his hand.</p>
            <p>The companie of <hi>la Chastre</hi> was ouerthrowne by <hi>Rubenpré.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Corbeil</hi> and <hi>Melun</hi> are taken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ville-Roy</hi> was with the Duke <hi>de Mayne</hi> at <hi>Sois<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sous.</hi> Monsieur <hi>du Plessis</hi> is gone to meete with him at <hi>Laigny:</hi> at his returne we shall knowe more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine newes.</p>
            <p>The Gouernour of <hi>Daulphiné,</hi> and the Lord of <hi>Diguieres</hi> and others the Kings seruitors haue taken in <hi>Grenoble,</hi> and reduced the rest of the Prouince into his Maiesties obedience.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>
               <hi>An Extract of things registred in</hi> the Court of Parliament.</head>
            <p>VPon relation made by the Kings Proctor ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, that as well by the Edicts of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, as also by the Acts of Parliament, hath been set downe and enioyned to all Bailiefes, their Lieftenants and other Iudges, to proceede diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to the seising of goods moueables and immoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables appertaining to the Leaguers &amp; Rebels, their complices and adherents, and to the sale of the said moueables and immoueables for the behoofe and profite of the King: albeit the said Bailiefes and their Lieftenants haue hetherto so negligently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in the executions thereof, that little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:190336:19"/>at all is yet come into the hands of the Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, the said Proctor generall requiring, that it would please the court of Parliament to take some order herein.</p>
            <p>The said Court dooing iustice herein, hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned and set downe verie straitlie to all Bailiefes of this companie, and to their deputies in euery Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countie, that they shall foorthwith, all other affaires set apart, proceede to the seising of all the goods moueables or immoueables, debts and actions of Leaguers and Rebels, their complices and adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, as well Clergie men and Nobles, as other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour pesants, and to sell the said moueables or immoueables to him that proffereth most for the same: and the deniers that shall arise thereof, to bee put by them into the hands of the Kings ordinarie Receiuers of his Demaine in euerie Vicountie: vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon paine to the contrarie, that the said Bailiefes and their deputies in case of negligence, forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or collusion in the execution of this present Act, shalbe condemned in their proper and priuate names in sommes counteruaillant the valour and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimation of the said moueables, and reuenue of the immoueables, and expresse Commissioners to bee sent at their charges to execute the said Arrest vpon the places, according to the forme and tenure. And to the end that this be not without effect; the saide Court hath ordained and enioyned to all the saide Bailiefes and deputies, to send euerie moneth to the Clarke of the same the verball processe of all seisies and sales of moueables &amp; immoueables that
<pb facs="tcp:190336:19"/>shall bee made, and the accompt of such deniers which shall arise thereby, and the which they haue put into the hands of the Receiuers of the Kings yearelie demaines of euerie of the said Vicounties, vpon like penaltie as aforesaid. And to the end that no man pretend anie ignorance herein; the Court hath ordained that this Edict shall bee printed and sent throughout all Bayliwickes, that in euerie of their Iurisdictions it may bee published and regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred, and a Copie of the said publication to be sent vnto the Clarke of the said Court, that recourse may bee had thereunto when neede shall require. Proclaimed at <hi>Caen</hi> in open Parliament, the 24. day of March. 1590.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed, <hi>Godfroy.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:190336:20"/>
            <head>An Acte of Parliament against <hi>those that harbor Rebels and Theeues,</hi> and helpe them to passe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe the Riuers.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>HEnry,</hi> by the grace of God, king of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and of <hi>Nauarre:</hi> To all our Bayliffes, Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, &amp; Prouosts, or to their Lieutenants, Generals, and Counsellers, to the first Porter of our Court of Parliament, or to any other of our Serge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants sendeth greeting: That whereas our Proctor generall hath made declaration to our Court, that diuerse rebells and other theeues, enemies of the peaceable estate of the common weale, do runne ouer countries, take prisoners and commit diuerse robberies and pillages on our poore liege subiects, and doo carry them away with them prisoners in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Townes and places detayned by the saide re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells, and are also for the same cause fauoured by diuers Gentlemen, who giue them aduise, and are priuy to their dealings, and doo take and receiue them into their houses and castells: Likewise, how that by boatmen and other ferry men which passe and repasse them ouer the riuers and waters, so that they haue great safety in their iourneys and wayes, demaunding that some order may be heerein ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Our saide Court hath made inhibition and defence to all Seigneurs, Gentlemen, and other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, of what qualitie or estate soeuer they be, to take in at any time, or receiue into their houses or
<pb facs="tcp:190336:20"/>forts the said Rebels, Theeues, and others of naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty life, to giue them any aduise, force, or aide in any sort whatsoeuer. But also to the contrary are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioined them to set vpon them, and to deliuer them into the hands of the Iustice, if it be possible, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise to cut them in peeces, vpon paine to be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely punished themselues, as adherents of the said rebels, and infractors of the arrests of our saide Court; hath made also expresse defence &amp; inhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to al boatmen &amp; ferrimen to passe or repasse the said Rebells, Theeues, and others of naughty life o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the riuer of <hi>Loire</hi> at any time, or to receiue thē, or to do any message for them, vpon paine of being broken on a wheele, hath declared and doth declare from henceforth as then, and then as now, and for euer hereafter, all the said theeues, and all their said receiuers, fauourers, and complices to be traytours in the highest degree. Dooth ordaine and ratifie, that all castells and forts that haue serued them for places of retraict, to be beaten downe and battered, and all other mansions and territories that thereto belong: also that all and euery of their goodes shall be tyed and retailed to our demaine without any hope euer hereafter to be seuered againe. Hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned and doth inioyne to all Bailiffes, Prouosts, Vicestewards, their deputies and other officers, to proceede against the said Rebells, Theeues, and all shall withstand and take their partes, and to punish them as aforesaid: and following the statutes and ordinaunces in this behalfe established; wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund all Gouernours of Townes and Castles to
<pb facs="tcp:190336:21"/>helpe them, and to cary the Cannon before the said place, if neede so require. And we commaund ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly the deputies and substitutes of our said Proc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour generall, and the receiuers of our demaines to looke well herevnto, and to keepe and render a iust account of the receit of all such deniers as shall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise of the saide demaines to be employed in case of warre, vpon paine to answere the contrary in their owne names and persons. And the saide deputies shalbe bound from fifteen dayes to fifteen dayes, to aduertise our saide Court of that which shall bee doone in the execution of this Act, the which our saide Court dooth ordaine and commaunde to be read and published thorowout all Bailiwikes, iuris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of Stewards, and Prouosts, Vicounts, and other places of like resort where are any sittings, or plees held, in all parish Churches, and to be set vp by proclamations on the gates of the palaces &amp; auditories at the labour and trauel of the said depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our said Proctor generall, to the end, that no resistance be made herein, &amp; that no cause of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance be hereafter pretended. At the request of our said Proctor generall, we command to put the said Arrest in full execution, according to his forme and tenure: Constraining all those to whome it shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine to execute and obey the same. Also we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly commaund and inioine al our Iustices, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and other subiects, to obey vnto you heerein. Giuen at <hi>Tours</hi> in our Court of Parliament the 27. Ian. the yeare of Grace 1590. and in the first yeare of our raigne.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed: <hi>La Chambre Denis.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:190336:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>